hey everyone welcome to another lesson
in the stsa automation course now in
previous videos I have shown you how you
can create your test case design sheet
how you can link it to a template and
then how you can create different
template instances out of your test case
design sheet and your test case
template now today I'm going to show you
how you can conditionally create
different test case template instances
now what does it mean is depending on
some condition some test step would be
part of a particular instance and at the
same time if that condition is not
satisfied then that test step will not
be part of a particular instance right
so you need that flexibility because not
all the test steps should be part of
every instance okay so let's look at a
real example so I'm going to take up uh
the same example which where we have
developed this template instance for
validate login now if I go to test case
design and if we look at these two
instances right so one is of valid user
and one is loged user now in this uh
scenario what we are doing is for loged
user it will throw a error message and
we want to validate it so we have put
this verification but the same
verification does not apply for a valid
user because there is no error message
and uh we don't want to validate this
particular error message or any kind of
verification for this valid user right
but uh when you link this test case
design sheet to your template what will
happen is it will create uh two
instances okay but it will have the same
steps uh irrespective of the fact that
there is no validation error uh
for for a valid user but the step still
exists so during execution also uh
although this uh there is not no values
here so it won't execute this step or it
will execute the step but it will not
perform any action and in the loged user
it will go ahead and validate uh or
verify this error message right but in
real world scenario uh you don't want uh
when there are lots of different steps
you don't want to confuse uh the tester
and put all the U all the test steps for
all the different instances right you
should be having some business logic
based on which you will have different
types of test cases or test instances
right and the flow of uh those test case
instances should be different based on
some business logic right now that is
where condition comes into picture and
you conditionally instantiate your test
cases based on some business logic right
so let's see how you can do this right
how we can uh make this uh verification
message test step to go away right in
one of our template instance for valid
user so we don't require this validate
error test step in a valid user test
case we just require it for locked user
right so that's that's our uh scenario
that's what we want to achieve and I'm
going to tell you how you can do that in
tosa okay
so the first step for this is to go to
your test case template and here uh we
need another column called condition
okay now the same way uh we have to do
uh we have to go to column Chooser and
here we have to find our column and we
can drag and drop it or just double
click it to add it to our test case
template okay now uh we have got a
condition
column now we have to put some condition
on our validate error test step right so
here uh either we can type uh the
condition or we can do a drag and drop
the recommended way uh of tosa is to
drag and drop the condition and not type
it so uh so that you don't make any
mistakes okay so uh we have to drag it
from the test case design sheet so let
me just pull this aside so that uh we
can have a
look Okay so
so uh let's open our test case template
and here we want to put a condition in
this particular step right and what we
want to do is we want to put some
business logic here right so what would
be our business logic so in case of a
user when it is the username is standard
user uh the password Remains the Same
right so it doesn't change but the
username changes so when it is a logged
out user uh it throws this error message
and that's our business logic right so
when the username equals to logged out
user then go ahead and verify or execute
that particular step otherwise don't do
it right if it is standard user we don't
want to do it okay
so either um you can have a step like uh
not equals to standard user or you can
have a step where username equals to
lockout user okay uh for me um I will do
the second one where uh I want to put
this username logged out user right uh
into my test case condition okay or my
test step condition so to do that uh you
need to go to your instances right so
expand the instances and then uh drag
and drop this logged out user instance
into our condition okay now as soon as
we drag this so let me close or bring
this to the center
let's go to our test case template right
now if you look at this condition column
okay for this validate
error and you will see here the logic
here is process do username equals
equals logged out user okay so I can
also type this um directly in this
condition column but I will follow the
recommended way of dragging and dropping
that particular instance into this uh
column and that will create a condition
for me automatically okay so whenever uh
this process. username equals equals
this then only it will go ahead and
instantiate it so while instantiating it
it will either skip this or it will add
this step okay and uh whenever you see
uh this particular Arrow Signs with two
dots okay then it is clear that this is
a conditional test step okay for um
normal two arrows it is a normal uh test
step for two arrows with two dots then
uh it is a conditional test step okay so
wherever you see this you should be
clear that this is a conditional test
step okay um now we have made changes to
our template right now we have to
reinstantiate our template instances so
that it creates the right test cases for
us okay so let's go go to our template
instance um and now you can see that all
the test steps are same but that's going
to change okay so right click and go
ahead and reinstantiate the
instance and you will see that tosa
automatically removed the test step for
the valid user but the locked user still
has that t step and that is because of
our condition Okay so so this is how
when you are creating hundreds of test
cases and you want to put some business
logic while creating this test cases you
have to use the condition column okay so
you should put it in your template and
then reinstantiate uh your template so
that the right kind of instances are
created uh with the right kind of
business
logic so that was all about uh uh
reinstantiate of your test cases with
condition
look out for more videos uh on our
Channel related to tosa coming up pretty
soon